<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title><![CDATA[@unmonoqueteclea - blogging]]></title>
<description><![CDATA[@unmonoqueteclea - blogging]]></description>
<link>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tag-blogging.html</link>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 21:55:03 +0100</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[towards minimalism]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
<b>tldr</b> I moved the blog to an extremely simple static blog generator
with no dependencies, no <code>Javascript</code> and no magic tricks. Just plain
<code>HTML</code> and <code>CSS</code>.
</p>

<p>
If you have been following this blog for some time you will have
noticed that I am not very good at keeping a routine of writing new
blog posts every week (or even every month). There was something that
created a lot of friction in the writing process (even more than the
white paper syndrome): every time I wanted to add new content, usually
after some months with no content, the blog build process was
broken. I spent more time fixing the blog than adding content to
it. This made me move to lightweight blogging systems like <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>. But
it wasn't enough so I decided to embrace minimalism.
</p>

<p>
What is the very minimal list of features that I need in a blogging
framework?:
</p>

<ul class="org-ul">
<li>Convert from markup languages such as <code>markdown</code> or <code>org-mode</code> into
plain <code>html</code></li>
<li>Keep an updated <b>index</b> page</li>
<li>Automatically create a <code>rss.xml</code> file</li>
<li>Automatically create an <b>archive</b> page and, ideally, another page for
each <b>tag</b></li>
</ul>

<p>
Just that. Those are the only things that I need. And that is what
<a href="https://github.com/bastibe/org-static-blog">org-static-blog</a> gives me. One single dependency, integrated into
<code>Emacs</code>, my OS (well&#x2026; my code editor). No <code>Javascript</code>, just pure <code>HTML</code>
and <code>CSS</code>.
</p>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tag-blogging.html">blogging</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[blogging]]></category>
  <link>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2022-12-26-towards-minimalism.html</link>
  <guid>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2022-12-26-towards-minimalism.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
