<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title><![CDATA[@unmonoqueteclea - projects]]></title>
<description><![CDATA[@unmonoqueteclea - projects]]></description>
<link>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tag-projects.html</link>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 08:22:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[the technology behind Voilib]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
In December 2022, I launched <a href="https://voilib.com">Voilib</a>, a podcast search engine. A few
months ago, I made the decision to make it <a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2023-07-02-voilib-is-now-open-source.html">Open Source</a>, allowing other
people to host their own instances to transcribe and index their
favorite podcasts. You can find it on <a href="https://github.com/unmonoqueteclea/voilib">Github</a> or <a href="https://gitlab.com/unmonoqueteclea/voilib">Gitlab</a> 🎉.
</p>

<p>
Hundreds of podcast episodes are <b>collected</b> and <b>transcribed</b> by the
system every week. This information is then <b>indexed</b> in a way that
allows semantic search so that users are able to perform smart queries to
find relevant fragments of podcast episodes.
</p>


<p>
Essentially, <a href="https://voilib.com">Voilib</a>'s work can be divided into four main tasks:
<b>collecting</b> new episodes, <b>transcribing</b> them, <b>indexing</b> all the content,
and <b>querying</b> the database to find relevant fragments.
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org8247575" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org8247575">🌐  collect (new episodes)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8247575">
<p>
Almost all public podcasts have an associated <code>RSS feed</code> that contains
metadata about every episode and even a link to the audio file. As an
example, <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TEDTalks_audio">this</a> is the <code>RSS feed</code> from the <a href="https://www.ted.com/about/programs-initiatives/ted-talks/ted-talks-daily">Ted Talks Daily</a> podcast.
</p>

<p>
Voilib uses those feeds to collect and store <b>metadata</b> from the list of
podcasts manually configured by the application admin. For each
episode, we are storing things such as the title, the description, the
language or the duration in a <code>SQLite</code> database.
</p>

<p>
When I want to check if new episodes were published, I just need to
run (I have a <b>cron job</b> configured to run it twice a day):
</p>

<div class="org-src-container">
<pre class="src src-bash">voilib-episodes --update
</pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-org00aa2e6" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org00aa2e6">🗨️ transcript (episodes audios)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org00aa2e6">
<p>
The collected episodes are then <b>transcribed</b> using <a href="https://openai.com/research/whisper">Whisper</a>: Open AI's
Open Source Transcription Model. We are using it, from <code>Python</code>, with
the library <a href="https://github.com/sanchit-gandhi/whisper-jax">whisper-jax</a>. This specific implementation of Whisper
boasts being up to 70 times faster than similar libraries.
</p>

<p>
In my opinions, those optimizations are very GPU focused and I cannot
find huge improvements in CPU compared with the <a href="https://github.com/openai/whisper">official
implementation</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-orgcc0a840" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="orgcc0a840">📇 index (episodes trancriptions)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgcc0a840">
<p>
Episodes transcripts are divided into fragments of approximately 40
words . Then, Voilib calculates the embedding of each fragment. In
that way, every fragment is converted into a vector of 384 floating
point numbers (check EMBEDDINGS<sub>SIZE</sub> constant to see the embedding size
currently used). Those vectors are stored in a vector database:
Qdrant.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org56f5f69" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="org56f5f69">🔍 query (transcription fragments)</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org56f5f69">
<p>
For each new user prompt, Voilib just needs to calculate the embedding
of it and find the closest ones in the vector database, returning the
most relevant episodes fragments to the user.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tag-projects.html">projects</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[projects]]></category>
  <link>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2023-08-03-the-technology-behind-voilib.html</link>
  <guid>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2023-08-03-the-technology-behind-voilib.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 20:26:00 +0200</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title><![CDATA[voilib is now open source]]></title>
  <description><![CDATA[
<p>
Today, I decided to <b>open-source</b> <a href="https://voilib.com">Voilib</a> 🎉, the podcast search engine I
launched in December 2022. You can now <b>run your own instance</b> of it and
transcribe and index your favorite podcasts (or even your own
content!).You can find it on <a href="https://github.com/unmonoqueteclea/voilib">Github</a> or <a href="https://gitlab.com/unmonoqueteclea/voilib">Gitlab</a>.
</p>

<p>
Appearing in <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34115618">Show
HN</a> was a big boost for the project. That post was the main source of
traffic during the first days of life of <a href="https://voilib.com">Voilib</a>. I am thrilled to see
that many of those initial users still use it today to discover
relevant podcast episodes on topics they are interested in. Throughout
these months, I have received valuable feedback and kind words from
some of them.
</p>


<figure id="org8392267">
<img src="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/static/feedback-voilib.png" alt="feedback-voilib.png" width="100%">

<figcaption><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Feedback from a Voilib user</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
Since I am not offering <code>Voilib PRO</code> any more (I may talk about this in
the future) the only funding for this project, to at least cover
server expenses, will come from <a href="https://ko-fi.com/unmonoqueteclea">donations</a> and <a href="https://ko-fi.com/unmonoqueteclea/commissions">customized assistance</a> to
people maintaining their own instances.
</p>

<p>
In the following weeks (well&#x2026; maybe months), I will publish some
blog posts explaining how the system works. I consider this is the
kind of content I would have loved to find some months ago when many
people suddenly became <code>prompt engineers</code>, but not so many people really
understood how to build actual LLM-based products beyond the chat
interface.
</p>
<div class="taglist"><a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tags.html">Tags</a>: <a href="https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/tag-projects.html">projects</a> </div>]]></description>
  <category><![CDATA[projects]]></category>
  <link>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2023-07-02-voilib-is-now-open-source.html</link>
  <guid>https://unmonoqueteclea.github.io/2023-07-02-voilib-is-now-open-source.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 12:32:00 +0200</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
